

#### **Contact info**

ignaciosticco@gmail.com +54 (9) 11-6045-0304 Argentina https://ignaciosticco.github.io/

## Languages

Spanish (native) English (B2 level)

## **Programming**

Python (Pandas, Numpy, Scipy, etc.)

Matlab

C++

**LAMMPS** 

Linux

Git

Latex

# Knowledge

**Statistics** 

**Physics** 

Math

#### **Skills**

Data analysis Programming Research

Data visualization

Data wrangling

Communication

Critical thinking

Creativity

Teaching

Continuous learning

# Ignacio Mariano Sticco

# Physicist & Data Scientist

#### About me

I hold a degree in Physics, and I am currently a part-time university professor while completing my Ph.D. in Physical Sciences at the University of Buenos Aires. The goal of my Ph.D. is to optimize a mathematical model for emergency evacuations and propose solutions for these evacuations. Throughout my academic career, I have gained extensive knowledge in predictive models, statistics, programming, artificial intelligence, and data science. I am interested in leveraging this expertise to apply Machine Learning to solve high-impact problems.

#### Education

**Ph.D. in Physics –** 2018 - 2023 (about to finish) *Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales (UBA)* 

Licenciatura in Physics – 2010 -2016 Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales (UBA)

## Work experience

#### Doctoral Fellow (CONICET) - 2018 - Present

- Conducted a comprehensive literature review in my field of research (Active learning).
- I developed computer programs to simulate emergency crowd evacuations, using C++ for the back-end and LAMMPS for the front-end.
- To analyze and visualize the results from numerical simulations, I primarily used Python, including popular packages such as Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, Pylab, Trackpy, and Sys. In some cases, I also utilized Matlab and Excel for additional analyses.
- I Implemented an evolutionary algorithm (artificial intelligence) from scratch to optimize the parameters of a model.
- Developed challenging tasks that required critical thinking and creativity. These tasks
  helped me further refine my expertise and better understand the intricacies of my field
  of research.

### Professor (Universidad Argentina de la Empresa- UADE) - 2021- Present

- Taught courses in General Physics and Electricity and Magnetism for engineering students.
- Led courses with over 50 students.
- Prepared and delivered classes in both in-person and virtual formats.
- Prepared and evaluated partial and final exams.
- Prepared and led laboratory hands-on sessions.
- Responded to student inquiries both in person and virtually.

## **Interests**

Artificial Intelligence
Science & Technology
Economy
Debating
Swimming & Gym
Cooking

#### Data Scientist (Futbol Sites Network) - 2018

- Use KPIs to quantify the performance of different websites.
- Create dashboards to report important metrics to other members of the company.
- Use Datorama, Google Analytics, Excel, and SQL.
- Found interesting patterns of user behavior.
- Extracted valuable data from JSON files.
- Linear regressions and measures of correlation.
- Time series and fluctuation analysis.

**Professor (FCEN, UBA)** - 2017 – 2018

## Peer-reviewed journal articles

I wrote and published 9 scientific papers in top-tier indexed journals.

Highlighted paper:

#### Social force model parameter testing and optimization using a high stress reallife situation

I.M. Sticco, G.A. Frank, C.O. Dorso, Physica A, 2020

In this paper, I extracted empirical data that resembles an emergency evacuation scenario. I tested a pedestrian dynamic model using different parameters proposed in scientific literature. Then, I developed an evolutionary algorithm to find a parameter set that fits the simulation model to the empirical data.

For more information, please refer to my Google Scholar profile

## **Data Science portfolio**

(See my personal website for more details: <a href="https://ignaciosticco.github.io">https://ignaciosticco.github.io</a>)

- NLP for Google maps reviews
- Hand Digit recognition (Neural Network)
- Pedestrian tracking
- Analysis of the bus network in the city of Buenos Aires

#### **Courses and Certifications**

7th Workshop on Collaborative Scientific Software Development – (2019)

ICTP Trieste (Italy)

Machine Learning – (2018)

Stanford University (Coursera)

**Learning how to learn** – (2015)

UC San Diego (Coursera)

First Certificate in English (B2) – (2009)

Cambridge